<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Aurora: or, A davvne to day-light.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75799</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A4232</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E448_1</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864187</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864187</idno>
            <idno type="VID">161821</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75799)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 161821)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 71:E448[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Aurora: or, A davvne to day-light.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare, 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A pamphlet in favor of the King" - Thomason Catalogue.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 16th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Political science --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:161821:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AURORA: <hi>OR,</hi> A DAWNE <hi>TO</hi> DAY-LIGHT.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Poſt tenebras lucem.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed in the Yeare, 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:161821:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:161821:2"/>
            <head>AVRORA: OR, <hi>A Dawne to Day-light.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He night now begins to draw up her <hi>fable Sailes,</hi> and lets downe to us a <hi>ſpringing Twi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light;</hi> which though <hi>faint</hi> and <hi>thin,</hi> yet after ſo <hi>thick</hi> a darkneſſe (as of late years hath <hi>Curtain'd</hi> o're this <hi>Iſland</hi>) brings much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort with it. The <hi>Morne</hi> (like a recovering ſick man) looks yet <hi>pallid</hi> &amp; <hi>puling;</hi> and though it be nothing comparable to that <hi>light</hi> the <hi>eye</hi> is capable of, (nor its fulleſt receipt but the ſatisfying the <hi>fift part</hi> of a ſenſible Creature:) yet it ſeems dreſt in a <hi>fuller</hi> Clarity, becauſe it appeares after ſo <hi>black</hi> a ſtorme. This dubious <hi>duskiſhneſſe</hi> preſents our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Actions confuſed, like their <hi>ſtories</hi> if woven in <hi>Arras,</hi> when we look upon the <hi>knotted</hi> out-ſide: or as if an <hi>ancient Eye</hi> ſhould goe about to reade them in a <hi>ſmall print.</hi> Here we may perceive men walke like <hi>trees,</hi> but Affaires being mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged beyond the levell of the <hi>Eye;</hi> we cannot reach to a <hi>perfect</hi> diſcovery. And yet methinks this inlarging <hi>Dawne</hi> promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:161821:3"/>a <hi>Birth</hi> that ſhall <hi>terminate</hi> our <hi>adverſities,</hi> and grow to a ſtrength able to <hi>diſcloud</hi> our long <hi>night:</hi> That theſe <hi>new-borne-rayes</hi> will <hi>gild</hi> our ſadned hearts, and <hi>burniſh</hi> o're our duller <hi>Hopes.</hi> If then hitherto we have been wilfully <hi>blind,</hi> let not our eyes prove <hi>enemies</hi> to us ſtill; but let us rather teare out that <hi>thick filme</hi> to make uſe of this beneficiall <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect:</hi> And perhaps if this <hi>Day-break</hi> lend us but ſo much <hi>light</hi> as to lead us into a <hi>path,</hi> our going forward may happily bring us to our <hi>owne doores.</hi> To the attaining of which won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted bleſſing, this <hi>early light</hi> promiſeth faire, and ſeemes to <hi>degree</hi> it ſelfe by the more noble <hi>ſurpriſall,</hi> becauſe ſo unexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctedly let in upon us. For ſeeing it enables us already to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh the <hi>benefit</hi> of our <hi>appearing comforts</hi> from the <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery</hi> of <hi>paſt misfortunes,</hi> let us make uſe of it to <hi>further</hi> the one, though we cannot <hi>remedy</hi> the other, and by <hi>deteſting</hi> the <hi>authors</hi> of our <hi>woes,</hi> make way to <hi>recrowne</hi> the <hi>finiſher</hi> of our <hi>happineſſe.</hi> In expectance of which future good, let us create to our ſelves this preſent benefit, to ſummon all our <hi>powers</hi> and <hi>faculties</hi> into our <hi>Eyes,</hi> (calling them there to councell) and then they will the better ſatisfie our <hi>judgement:</hi> though on the ſudden our <hi>thoughts</hi> are <hi>ravell'd</hi> into diſorder, becauſe burthened with <hi>hopes, feares, doubts, deſires, ſuſpicions,</hi> and <hi>amazements;</hi> like <hi>waters</hi> forſaking that <hi>by-ditch</hi> which the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilful <hi>Drayners</hi> of theſe times, drew them into, and are try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeverall <hi>Channels</hi> to returne to their right ſtreame. This <hi>glimmering light</hi> thus hopefully aſſuring us the reſtauration of a <hi>Day,</hi> we may be all partakers of the beneficiall happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereof if we pleaſe. But how welcome to the <hi>Royall partie,</hi> (whoſe tedious habitation in ſuch an impriſoned <hi>ſhade</hi> have often forc'd them to ſigh out that complaint of good old <hi>Tobie, Quale gaudium eſt mihi quia in tenebris ſedeo?</hi>) None can more truely know, ſave thoſe whoſe deſperate and weighty <hi>miſeries,</hi> have made them more capable of the worth
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:161821:3"/>of ſo large a <hi>bleſsing.</hi> The <hi>expectation</hi> whereof is <hi>pleaſant,</hi> but our <hi>fruition more pleaſant;</hi> what now <hi>nouriſheth</hi> our <hi>ſpringing hopes,</hi> ſhall then <hi>crowne</hi> our full grown <hi>enjoyment.</hi> In the meane time let us (like the <hi>pleaſed birds</hi>) forſake theſe long confined <hi>nests,</hi> to <hi>prune</hi> our dull and unrefreſhed <hi>thoughts,</hi> and with our cheerfulleſt <hi>notes</hi> thank <hi>Heaven</hi> for this <hi>Day-break.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that we may ſet a greater value upon the <hi>promiſed day,</hi> let us reflect a little upon our <hi>paſt night;</hi> where we may ſee our <hi>Sun</hi> totally ſwallowed up by <hi>darkneſſe,</hi> and our <hi>Moon</hi> wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding through an <hi>envious Eclipſe; Stars</hi> of the firſt <hi>magnitude</hi> maskt o're with <hi>clouds,</hi> and thouſands of our <hi>fixed lamps</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>wandring Planets:</hi> our chiefeſt <hi>Tapers</hi> puft or ſnuft out, or elſe <hi>lanthorn'd</hi> in an <hi>impriſon'd dungeon.</hi> In fine, (to our diſcomfort) we may behold our <hi>Glories</hi> blurr'd, and all our <hi>comforts</hi> Tarniſhed. But happy we, if this <hi>Twi-light</hi> uſher us the way to view a <hi>glimpſe</hi> of our former condition, perhaps it may lead us to a fuller proſpect, where we may ſee the <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> of this Nation growne up to the top of the <hi>ſpire,</hi> and <hi>Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe</hi> dreſt in her fulleſt <hi>flouriſh,</hi> where pleaſures were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented with a <hi>towring</hi> delight, and our <hi>Gardens</hi> wanted no beautifull trimming. Who grew <hi>waſpiſh</hi> when any queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd our Title of <hi>preſcription</hi> for <hi>Proſperity,</hi> and thought <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> did us much injury to ſue forth a Writ <hi>De executione De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretis</hi> for the poſſeſſion of that we had enjoyed <hi>Time out of mind?</hi> But alas! pernitious <hi>weeds</hi> grew up with theſe <hi>flowers, Omne in praecipiti vitium ſtetit.</hi> We <hi>(quam Jocus circumvolat)</hi> were <hi>too happy</hi> and <hi>proud,</hi> which made us <hi>wanton,</hi> and lo! in an inſtant <hi>wilfull Reſolution</hi> drawing the <hi>Curtaine,</hi> the <hi>flowers</hi> of our <hi>felicity</hi> were ſtraight forgot, <hi>&amp; nunc non erat his locus:</hi> Such fruit as our induſtrious <hi>Summer</hi> nouriſht, our deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Winter</hi> hath utterly periſht: and yet we doe not feelingly deplore our <hi>unhappineſſe,</hi> as the depth of it exacts. And
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:161821:4"/>though an eternall and never-fading <hi>youth</hi> ſeemed to be conferr'd upon us, as the <hi>Gods</hi> did upon <hi>Prometheus</hi> off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring, yet we (like them) fooliſhly entruſted this bounteous gift to the ſilly <hi>Aſſe,</hi> who for a draught of <hi>water</hi> ſold it to <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents.</hi> Nor ſtaid we here at this loſſe, for our further impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence gained us the title of <hi>adoption</hi> to <hi>Epimetheus,</hi> when we ſo greedily accepted of <hi>Pandora's</hi> proſtituted <hi>Box,</hi> which (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving as raſhly opened) let out all <hi>misfortunes</hi> upon us; (onely we had ſo much diſcretion to retaine <hi>Hope</hi> in the <hi>bottome.</hi>) For at the firſt view of theſe late <hi>Troubles,</hi> how falſe did our hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous and purblind <hi>eyes</hi> ſee? and yet renouncing them, what deceitfull and perverſe <hi>ſpectacles</hi> have we ever ſince truſted? How did we ſuffer our <hi>miſchiefes</hi> to ſteale in upon us like an <hi>Hectick Feaver</hi> (that in the beginning was <hi>difficult</hi> to be <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcovered,</hi> and <hi>eaſie</hi> to be <hi>avoided,</hi> but at length became more <hi>eaſily knowne,</hi> and <hi>harder</hi> to be <hi>cured:</hi>) and which, <hi>ſicut unda ſequitur undam,</hi> like water in the ſea, one throng'd into the neck of another. At what a rate did we <hi>hire</hi> a <hi>War,</hi> and how many vaſt ſummes did we bring in to throw away?</p>
            <q>
               <l>—neque enim loculis comitantibus itur</l>
               <l>Ad caſum Tabulae, poſita ſed luditur arca.</l>
            </q>
            <p>How raſhly did we <hi>mow</hi> down our <hi>well-grown</hi> happineſſe? and how haſt ly did we <hi>obnubulate</hi> our <hi>ful-ſpread</hi> glories? How did we <hi>ſpurne</hi> at that precious jewell, <hi>Peace?</hi> and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging its Grave, bury all that we could call <hi>comfort,</hi> in it? How did we chaſe our ſelves into deſtruction with a <hi>ſharpned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ur, (hac Tuba rixa)</hi> never ſeeking to check the <hi>rains</hi> till we fell our ſelves over head and eares beyond recovery? and then ſtrugling againſt the <hi>tyde</hi> ſtriving to break thoſe threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ening <hi>waves</hi>) into how great dangers hath it intituled us? How did we burry our <hi>Sun</hi> into the <hi>Weſt</hi> being offended with
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:161821:4"/>the glory of too <hi>bright</hi> a <hi>Ray?</hi> How did we court a riſing and prodigious <hi>Moone,</hi> whoſe <hi>borrowed light</hi> onely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d us to an <hi>unwearied deſtruction? Fools</hi> that we were! to ruſh into a Quarrell in the Dark, when our <hi>ignorant-dealt</hi> blowes woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>friends</hi> as well as <hi>foes:</hi> Had our Swords been <hi>deliberate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> unſheath'd, (and in the <hi>Day</hi>) they might have diſcern'd the true <hi>oppoſite</hi> or known the way to their peacefull <hi>Scab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bards. Sed jam Serpentum major concordia:</hi> whilſt conteſting for <hi>Trifles,</hi> and ruſhing into the <hi>fray</hi> unadviſedly, in how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſad and deſtructive <hi>Dilemma's</hi> have our aſtoniſht thoughts been bound? What perilous and unknown <hi>Coaſts, Rocks, Flaws, Sands,</hi> and <hi>Shallowes,</hi> in this troubled <hi>Ocean,</hi> hath this <hi>darkned tempeſt</hi> driven us upon? ſo that indeed we ſeem'd loſt to all <hi>felicity;</hi> yet verily <hi>we have ſeen the wonders of the Lord in this great deep.</hi> And truly our <hi>diſaſters</hi> may not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitly be paralleld with the <hi>raging Seas,</hi> who are running and roaring with unreſiſtable force, and which every Minute threatens inevitable ruine; but thanks be to that <hi>protecting hand</hi> which hath ſupported many of our unweildy <hi>barkes,</hi> making the <hi>fidelity</hi> of that <hi>Element</hi> fully manifeſt in their <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation,</hi> and ſafely convey'd them to a promiſing-ſecure-<hi>Harbour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The confeſſed truth is, our <hi>proſperity</hi> was great, and we ſo fully <hi>poſſeſt</hi> of it, that (had we been as <hi>circumſpect</hi> as <hi>care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe</hi>) we might imagine <hi>adverſity</hi> could not be far off; which when it came (and comming ſo unexpectedly) did more roughly diſpoſſeſſe us of the <hi>bleſsings</hi> we injoy'd; then if we had met it with a <hi>prepared boſome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But our <hi>night</hi> it approach'd, and like that of <hi>Penelope's</hi> hath ravel'd and undone all that our <hi>day</hi> did weave; a <hi>night!</hi> (though <hi>nights</hi> be common and <hi>darkneſſe</hi> familiar to us yet this we may well beſtow a <hi>wonder</hi> upon) which overwhelm'd us in ſuch ſolid <hi>darkneſſe, darkneſſe</hi> ſo collected, that indeed
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:161821:5"/>it was <hi>felt;</hi> becauſe the <hi>ſhaded mantle</hi> was <hi>folded</hi> ſo many <hi>double.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>thick ſhades</hi> made us languiſh even to the utmoſt <hi>gaſpe,</hi> during which, if we ſaw any <hi>light</hi> at all, 'twas <hi>terible</hi> as <hi>lightning,</hi> and <hi>fatall</hi> as a <hi>comet;</hi> never appearing, but at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with deſtructive <hi>thunder:</hi> which left nothing behind but a <hi>feeble blew, dull</hi> and <hi>heavy</hi> as a <hi>melancholly ſnuffe</hi> expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in a <hi>ſocket.</hi> 'Tis true, that now and then, though our <hi>clouds</hi> were <hi>loaded</hi> with ſuch contracted <hi>ſhade,</hi> yet they affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a few ſeeming <hi>benefits,</hi> and opened the way to ſome fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming <hi>Meteors</hi> appearance; but immediately <hi>skrein'd</hi> them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, (and therein became friendly to us) leſt our over-ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger <hi>belief</hi> (giving to theſe <hi>falſe fires</hi> and credit of <hi>morning ſtars,</hi> ſhould lend us, hopes of an approaching <hi>twylight,</hi> which yet they were not pleas'd to diſco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> nor unlock thoſe <hi>early dores,</hi> for our long <hi>impriſoned Sun</hi> to ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
            <p>During theſe weighty <hi>afflictions,</hi> nothing ſeemed to <hi>prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſticate</hi> our ruine ſo much as the <hi>deſpairing hearts</hi> we carried about us; becauſe <hi>fortune</hi> continued ſo conſtant to her <hi>frownes;</hi> yet alas! that onely was in regard ſhe had a long while uſed us to them. But the ſame skill that <hi>ſatisfied</hi> us how our <hi>proſperity</hi> was maintain'd, might have <hi>foretold</hi> us of the approaching <hi>danger;</hi> Nay, yet we may thereby foreſee our <hi>deliverance</hi> if we will not live in reſolv'd <hi>blindneſs.</hi> And time it is, ſince 'tis our ſelves that ruine our ſelves, we can charge none elſe with the <hi>guilt.</hi> All our <hi>glory, wealth, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, happineſſe, comforts,</hi> and <hi>felicities,</hi> nay the choice of bleſſings, <hi>Peace!</hi> have been buried in a <hi>grave</hi> of our owne <hi>digging:</hi> and upon which no other <hi>monument</hi> muſt be ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, then the broken and ſcattered <hi>pyles</hi> of our owne <hi>ruines.</hi> Our former daies were the <hi>white paper,</hi> and our <hi>five yeares night,</hi> the <hi>Acts</hi> of our ſad <hi>Tragedies,</hi> written thereon not in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:161821:5"/>
               <hi>Inke,</hi> but in <hi>Bloud;</hi> making up the <hi>Volume</hi> of our paſt and preſent age: in which (without <hi>Spectacles</hi>) we may read the ſaddeſt <hi>loſſes</hi> ever came to a <hi>people.</hi> Never was <hi>Age</hi> ſo thick ſowne with the venemous <hi>ſpawne</hi> of <hi>Civill diſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> which (like <hi>Cadmus</hi> Teeth) immediately produced whole troups of <hi>Felo de ſe's:</hi> who (had they been wiſe) ſhould rather have imployed their <hi>Tongues</hi> in <hi>licking,</hi> then their <hi>Teeth</hi> in <hi>biting</hi> ſuch <hi>deep wounds.</hi> And for <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegious Imps, nature,</hi> nor <hi>liberty</hi> ever yet produced their equall. How many <hi>houſes of God</hi> have they <hi>deſtroyed</hi> in the Land! nay; what <hi>Church</hi> is it that hath ſcap'd <hi>plundering?</hi> Surely they that <hi>violate</hi> the <hi>place</hi> of <hi>Gods</hi> dwelling can never truly <hi>honour him.</hi> And as the <hi>Temples</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> ſo the <hi>Temples</hi> of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> (lay'd up there in a ſafe <hi>repoſe</hi>) have ſuffered <hi>pillaging.</hi> Having not ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ſtrip the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of ſuch <hi>robes,</hi> as <hi>pious hands</hi> had <hi>dreſt</hi> them in, to let <hi>Poſterity</hi> know them by their <hi>Monuments;</hi> nor forborne to <hi>ranſack</hi> them of their meaneſt <hi>clothes,</hi> their bare <hi>Coffins;</hi> leaving no <hi>Epitaph</hi> but (what they could not take away) the <hi>bloudy Veines</hi> in the remaining <hi>Marble.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Monuments</hi> were erected to <hi>preſerve</hi> and <hi>perpetuate</hi> the <hi>memories</hi> and <hi>noble actions</hi> of ſuch as have <hi>lived ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourably,</hi> and <hi>died vertuouſly,</hi> and no leſſe then a condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to the <hi>Gallies,</hi> or grinding at the <hi>Mill</hi> did our pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent <hi>Aunceſtors</hi> impoſe upon the <hi>Violators</hi> thereof, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the offence was reputed a crime <hi>infamous,</hi> and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall to <hi>Perjury;</hi> and the <hi>Offendour</hi> guilty both of <hi>Theft</hi> and <hi>Sacriledge:</hi> But I leave theſe deeds of <hi>darkneſſe,</hi> to be puniſhed by the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>darkneſſe,</hi> and proceed.</p>
            <p>We have now at length by wofull and dear-bought <hi>experience</hi> found, what private <hi>Machivilian</hi> power it was gave <hi>Law</hi> to <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and what <hi>clandeſtine</hi> projects (like
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:161821:6"/>the <hi>primum mobile</hi>) gave <hi>motion</hi> to theſe <hi>multitudes</hi> of <hi>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief.</hi> As for our <hi>Laws,</hi> like thoſe whereof <hi>Tacitus</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains, <hi>invalido legum auxilio, quae vi, ambitu, poſtremo pecunia turbabantur,</hi> they afford no ſecurity, being ſway'd hither and thither by <hi>might, ambition,</hi> and <hi>corruption.</hi> All that is now left us, is, to <hi>ſit down,</hi> &amp; <hi>number</hi> up our former <hi>bleſsings:</hi> A poor comfort! to look back upon theſe, and forward upon approaching <hi>miſeries:</hi> ſo that we may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcedly cry out in that patheticall exclamation, <hi>ô ubi e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes fontes lacrimarum!</hi> what is become of you ye <hi>foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines</hi> of <hi>teares!</hi> are you dried up by the <hi>preaching</hi> of <hi>hardned hearts?</hi> or converted into <hi>bloud,</hi> by the <hi>cracking</hi> of the <hi>eye-ſtrings?</hi> but our <hi>hopes,</hi> are, that our <hi>ſorrows</hi> and <hi>preſſures</hi> are <hi>skru'd</hi> up to their <hi>higheſt pitch,</hi> and <hi>itch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fingers</hi> being unwilling to leave them at that <hi>ſtay,</hi> the other <hi>wind</hi> may perchance break the <hi>ſtring;</hi> and ſo give <hi>freedome</hi> to an <hi>eſcape,</hi> from a <hi>ſuppoſed-inevitable-ruine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And then (as <hi>want</hi> ſhews the true <hi>valuation</hi> of that thing, our unexamined enjoyment made too <hi>cheap</hi>) when we are afforded ſo much <hi>light</hi> to ſee what we have ſo long loſt, ſure we ſhall more eſteem its <hi>return</hi> then when we <hi>poſſeſt</hi> it; and probably improve it to a better advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage; For, <hi>Dulce eſt nomen pacis &amp; res ipſa perquam ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tares,</hi> ſweet is the name and healthfull the nature of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Peace.</hi> But it will never appear in our <hi>Horizon,</hi> till our <hi>Kingly Sun</hi> ariſe again, upon whoſe <hi>Glory</hi> it waits as a neer attendant which will not be long now: for this <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> when <hi>ſhufled</hi> out of a regular courſe by any former diſtempers, like the wandring <hi>needle</hi> never left <hi>trembling,</hi> till it had ſetled it ſelf upon the <hi>point</hi> of <hi>Monarchy,</hi> to which it naturally owes <hi>affection.</hi> Yet to ſuch who mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer at the <hi>Snales</hi> pace, obſerved, in the carriage on of ſuch a <hi>deſigne</hi> as the <hi>reſtauration</hi> of a <hi>Crowne;</hi> and who
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:161821:6"/>impatiently ſtudy to adde <hi>wings</hi> to diſpatch, or lead on theſe affaires in a more direct <hi>path;</hi> let them know, <hi>nihil dictu facilius,</hi> Men may ſooner <hi>project</hi> then <hi>execute;</hi> nor may every <hi>projection</hi> be <hi>attempted,</hi> or every <hi>attempt, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu'd.</hi> That <hi>time</hi> is fitteſt which <hi>Heaven</hi> appoints, and <hi>bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe</hi> is then <hi>ripe,</hi> when the <hi>decree</hi> is ready to <hi>go forth.</hi> Nay, if we rightly conſider, we may highly prize the ſlow progreſſe this <hi>dawning</hi> makes; and think our happineſſe the more ſurely founded, when the <hi>day</hi> breaks on us <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datim.</hi> Sudden <hi>flaſhes</hi> affright with <hi>horror,</hi> and portend <hi>ſhort glories,</hi> when as a <hi>Twilight</hi> that hath a <hi>degreeing</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance promiſeth a <hi>ſerene</hi> and quiet <hi>Day.</hi> Should a <hi>Meridian luſter</hi> now <hi>raſh</hi> in upon us, it might <hi>dazle</hi> us with an ore-powerfull <hi>brightneſse;</hi> and tempt us beſide our truſty <hi>path,</hi> for <hi>ſenſibile fortè deſtruit ſenſum,</hi> too ſtrong an <hi>object</hi> vanquiſheth the <hi>ſight,</hi> and may perhaps <hi>chaſe</hi> us into a deluded <hi>precipitation.</hi> We have an old <hi>Adage,</hi> (and they ſeldome faile of <hi>verity</hi>) <hi>that</hi> (many times) <hi>the fartheſt way about, is the neareſt way home: Councels</hi> managed by a <hi>leiſurely progreſsion</hi> (if conceal'd) <hi>thrive beſt;</hi> though I confeſſe <hi>execution</hi> and <hi>diſpatch</hi> ſhould be driven on with a <hi>nimble hand.</hi> Let us not then <hi>afflict</hi> our <hi>hopes,</hi> by fearing they are <hi>over-lingered,</hi> but wait with a patient expectation of <hi>fruition</hi> in its ripeſt ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. What <hi>obſtructions</hi> have interveen'd, we are behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>London</hi> for, who might long ere this (had they been compoſed of any thing but <hi>diſ-loyall earth</hi> and <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidious baſeneſſe</hi>) have put faire for the <hi>re-inſtating</hi> of <hi>His Majeſty,</hi> and ſet a happy <hi>period,</hi> to ours, and their own long <hi>miſ-fortunes.</hi> But that <hi>City</hi> muſt <hi>ſmart, yet, againe,</hi> and a <hi>third time;</hi> that <hi>proud City!</hi> which being ſeated un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Aequinoctiall,</hi> and favour'd (above all) with a conſtant <hi>perpendicular ray;</hi> was never contented, till it
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:161821:7"/>had <hi>pick'd a quarrell</hi> with a <hi>Cryme</hi> of too much <hi>ſommer,</hi> and forc'd the <hi>Sun</hi> more <hi>Northward</hi> from it; but 'tis no matter, its <hi>ingratitude</hi> hath ſince been <hi>froſt-nipt</hi> with a multitude of coldeſt <hi>miſeries:</hi> and ſenſibly felt the ſmart of a periſhing <hi>winter.</hi> For, how many of its Inhabitants like <hi>Fiſhes,</hi> left on a dry ſhore, have periſhed? when <hi>His Majeſty</hi> (like a <hi>wave</hi>) remov'd, and how many fair-ſpred <hi>flowers</hi> in that royall <hi>Garden,</hi> (like the <hi>Helitropian</hi>) ſhrunk in their <hi>leaves</hi> when He departed? 'Twas appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent by the <hi>courſes</hi> of thoſe ruinous <hi>Tenants,</hi> that they took to themſelves <hi>Leaſes</hi> for many Lives without im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachment of <hi>waſt,</hi> but they will prove but <hi>Tenants</hi> at <hi>will:</hi> and now their <hi>Land-lords</hi> are about to out them, 'tis to no purpoſe to keep a forcible <hi>Deteynor.</hi> No, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their <hi>combination</hi> and <hi>league</hi> with that hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid <hi>darkneſſe</hi> which hath blaſted the face of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; and by which <hi>united cloſeneſſe</hi> they became a <hi>Cloyſter</hi> for <hi>crimes,</hi> and a <hi>ſhade</hi> to cover <hi>Sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>—maneant qui nigrum in candida vertunt,</l>
               <l>Queis facile eſt aedem conducere, flumina, portus.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Machivilians!</hi> whoſe <hi>clandeſtine</hi> contrivements have <hi>rock'd</hi> us into a <hi>lethargy,</hi> and led us into thoſe <hi>bloudy-blind Paths;</hi> which had we had our <hi>eyes</hi> open, no <hi>ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem</hi> (how plauſible ſoever) could ever have drawne us within its <hi>noſſe. Ambitious ſpirits!</hi> whoſe end was their owne <hi>oppulency</hi> and <hi>greatneſſe,</hi> and our <hi>indigence</hi> and <hi>vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalage. Pilates,</hi> and <hi>Herods!</hi> (for <hi>magna inter molles con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordia</hi>) whoſe bloudy <hi>confederacy,</hi> crucified <hi>Chriſt</hi> afreſh in his <hi>Members. Owles!</hi> what will now bluſh and vaniſh to behold the <hi>light,</hi> which muſt betray their baſeneſſe; but indeed theſe ſons of <hi>Terviah</hi> were too hard for us,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:161821:7"/>yet the <hi>juſtice</hi> of <hi>Heaven</hi> is moſt remarkable; for though through their <hi>dark</hi> practiſes, our glorious <hi>Sun</hi> became <hi>Eclips'd,</hi> yet have they ſuffered for want of his <hi>influence:</hi> Though the <hi>Culminating</hi> bold-fac'd <hi>Moone</hi> hath uſurp'd the <hi>regall houſe</hi> ever ſince, yet how ſharply the reines of her <hi>Government</hi> hath curb'd them, all yet miſerably feel. <hi>Culpam poena premit Comes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now if ever they mean to be <hi>ſaved,</hi> the chief <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle</hi> of their <hi>Creed</hi> muſt be in their <hi>Suns aſcenſion</hi> into <hi>Glory;</hi> and the next in their <hi>Moones deſcenſion</hi> into <hi>Hell:</hi> Their only hope muſt reſt in this, that when this worlds bright <hi>Eye</hi> appears again, he will look upon them, with his wonted <hi>compaſsion;</hi> to thaw the <hi>icy</hi> cold that hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numm'd them into a ſenſleſſe <hi>ſtupidity,</hi> and ſtifned them into <hi>Rebellion;</hi> and to diſperce amongſt them his uſuall nouriſhing <hi>influence.</hi> But the truth is, they have little de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd ſo large a bleſſing as his return, who have ſo long while unmask'd his favours, and put on a <hi>vizard;</hi> and in ſtead of rendring a <hi>pleaſed countenance,</hi> return'd an <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull menace.</hi> However I cannot altogether blame the <hi>Generality,</hi> though <hi>Omnes errorem bibunt,</hi> nor too ſharply cenſure the <hi>face</hi> of things, when preſented to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny through a falſe <hi>Glaſſe.</hi> 'Tis <hi>charity</hi> makes me ſo ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der herein, and withall I cannot but remember that of <hi>Ovid:</hi>
               <q>Parcite paucorum diffundere crimen in omnes.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I know, and confeſſe, <hi>Diſparagements</hi> are quickly <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim'd,</hi> but not ſo eaſily <hi>retriv'd:</hi> that <hi>affection</hi> and <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like</hi> are like the two ends of a <hi>Proſpective glaſſe,</hi> where the one <hi>leſſons,</hi> and the other <hi>multiplies. Silly Soules!</hi> their deluded <hi>underſtanding</hi> and groſſe <hi>ignorance,</hi> made many of them <hi>cenſorious;</hi> but ſuch as thought by <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:161821:8"/>to be eſteemed <hi>wiſe</hi> diſcovered themſelves the moſt malicious <hi>fools.</hi> What <hi>dark inſinuations</hi> were <hi>skr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'d</hi> into <hi>execution,</hi> to diſmount that <hi>awe</hi> &amp; <hi>reverence His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty</hi> juſtly held over His Subjects hearts? How many baſe conceptions were <hi>hiv'd</hi> in <hi>waſpiſh</hi> minds? their baſer <hi>Tongues</hi> uſurping the <hi>Bedles laſh;</hi> ſuch were the venome of <hi>blaſphemous mouths,</hi> and the undutifulneſſe of <hi>rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous prompters,</hi> but 'tis naturall for <hi>Dogs</hi> to bark againſt the <hi>Moone;</hi> and thoſe diſcreet judgments that had taken a <hi>Pill</hi> for this <hi>contagion,</hi> were not to be accounted unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py: for my ſelf (as <hi>Horace</hi> in another caſe)
<q>Quodcun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> oſtendit mihi ſic incredulus odi.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I have much wonder'd whence theſe <hi>detractions</hi> ſhould ſpring? unleſſe from the receipt of too large <hi>favours:</hi> and indeed when men become <hi>Bankrupts,</hi> their gratitude oft-times converts to <hi>diſcourteſies.</hi> But 'tis more won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull to conſider how ſo many <hi>quivers</hi> of ſcandalous <hi>arrows</hi> have been emptied out againſt <hi>His Majeſty,</hi> who yet ſtanding like the unpierc'd <hi>marble,</hi> hath <hi>ſhatter'd</hi> them all: which to mention is not ſo fit as to <hi>rake</hi> together and <hi>burne;</hi> leſt their <hi>ſplinters</hi> ſhould <hi>wrancle</hi> poſterity, who perhaps may want the ages <hi>ſalve, viz.</hi> a full and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible <hi>confutation:</hi> ſhould any of us indure ſo narrow an <hi>inquiſition</hi> into our <hi>actions,</hi> I feare we ſhould be found guilty of corrupt <hi>tinctures,</hi> our baſer <hi>mettals</hi> are too full of <hi>droſſe,</hi> but his <hi>Gold</hi> hath return'd out of the <hi>crucible</hi> without <hi>waſt.</hi> And yet (ô incomparable <hi>magnanimity!</hi>) though ſo abuſively <hi>detracted,</hi> doth offer to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe altogether incapable of future <hi>revenge,</hi> and what wounds theſe multiplied <hi>injuries</hi> have ſeemed to make; his not taking notice hath fully <hi>cured;</hi> or elſe his <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſſe</hi> ſhall weare out the <hi>ſcar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I can parallel <hi>His unfortunate Majeſty</hi> to none more fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:161821:8"/>then to that reſolute and couragious <hi>Athenian</hi> Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier; who being vanquiſhed in a <hi>navall</hi> fight, layed hold of one of his Enemies Ships, and when his <hi>right hand</hi> was cut off held faſt by the <hi>left,</hi> and when <hi>that</hi> was chopt off, maintain'd his hold with his <hi>Teeth.</hi> So <hi>His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty,</hi> loſing His own <hi>Army,</hi> betook His truſt to the <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide-Scot,</hi> that <hi>truſtleſſe</hi> and <hi>hypocriticall</hi> refuge; where loſing (as it were, His <hi>right hand</hi>) He held up His <hi>intereſt</hi> with the <hi>Independent,</hi> who as <hi>perfideouſly</hi> lopt off the <hi>left</hi> alſo; and left (to every judgment) no appearance of <hi>ſaving relief,</hi> and yet we ſee He ſtill preſerves His <hi>life</hi> and <hi>integrity</hi> with His <hi>laſt reſerve:</hi> a <hi>conſtant reſolution,</hi> which <hi>ſinewing</hi> with unweakned <hi>nerves,</hi> he holds them <hi>tugging, unwearied,</hi> and <hi>unremov'd:</hi> ſharpning the one to <hi>what</hi> His <hi>abilities</hi> for all <hi>Oppoſers,</hi> and <hi>ſweetning</hi> the other to oppoſe what His <hi>ſad fate</hi> hath too prodigally furniſhed Him with. Unkind <hi>fortune!</hi> why haſt thou dealt ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindly with Him in <hi>dealing</hi> His <hi>Cards?</hi> that if diſcreet and wary <hi>reſolution</hi> had not made Him a good <hi>Gameſter,</hi> the <hi>Set</hi> had been irrecoverably loſt. But His <hi>God</hi> is the ſame He was at the <hi>beginning,</hi> and <hi>now</hi> (as <hi>then</hi>) hath brought <hi>light</hi> out of <hi>darkneſſe.</hi> His Majeſty is become <hi>happy</hi> meerly by His <hi>unhappineſſe:</hi> and they are His <hi>misfortunes</hi> that have proclam'd His <hi>heroick</hi> worth. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance we had never taken notice of the <hi>luſtre</hi> of His <hi>wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> but through this black <hi>Eclipſe:</hi> nor of His even carriage in His <hi>ſinking adverſities,</hi> but by the rough <hi>ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering</hi> of the <hi>ſurly waves.</hi> His ſilent <hi>patience</hi> diſcovered His <hi>injuries</hi> more fully, then perhaps His publick <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints</hi> would, and ſo juſt a temper in all <hi>accidents</hi> did never appear in any <hi>breſt.</hi> His <hi>mildneſſe</hi> ſtill met them as <hi>yeilding wooll</hi> doth the ſtroke of <hi>iron;</hi> which is a more noble <hi>victory</hi> then that gain'd by <hi>oppoſition:</hi> Nay, of all
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:161821:9"/>
               <hi>victories,</hi> His, muſt needs be the greateſt, for He hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer'd His <hi>patience,</hi> and having laid a <hi>foundation</hi> upon ſo firme a <hi>vertue,</hi> His <hi>greatneſſe</hi> rear'd thereon cannot fall, eſpecially having the ſupport of many other. But now to conſider with what admirable <hi>conſtancy</hi> He hath <hi>wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd</hi> out this time of <hi>durance,</hi> tiring his <hi>adverſaries</hi> with complying <hi>ſufferance,</hi> (making his ſweet returns ſurer then <hi>golden baits</hi> to catch them with) leſt earneſt <hi>conteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> might ſtrike their <hi>ſharpned hooke</hi> the deeper into his <hi>ſides.</hi> All the <hi>provocations</hi> he hath been continually aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted (which to a <hi>ſlacking fury</hi> would have proved like <hi>bellowes</hi>) could never tranſport him in his loweſt eſtate, nor quicken him into any ſharp <hi>returns:</hi> and when new <hi>tortures</hi> were found out for his <hi>patience,</hi> they proved but as freſh <hi>invitements,</hi> to <hi>contract</hi> and <hi>knit</hi> it more <hi>firm</hi> and <hi>ſtronger;</hi> and this 'twas made his <hi>reſolution</hi> more <hi>ſolid</hi> and <hi>compact.</hi> Briefly, like a wiſe <hi>Phyſitian,</hi> he converted all their poyſonous <hi>drugs</hi> into a <hi>medicinable</hi> quality. And therefore the greateſt <hi>crime</hi> for which his <hi>preciſer</hi> Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries ſcoft at him, was, for being (like that antient <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian Patriarch</hi>) ſingly ſo <hi>good</hi> and <hi>pious,</hi> in ſo <hi>bad</hi> and <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious</hi> times: when <hi>turn-coat vices</hi> were ſo univerſally in faſhion. But theſe His <hi>Princely</hi> vertues of <hi>juſtice, wiſdom, clemency, courage,</hi> and <hi>devotion,</hi> have proved all <hi>aſsiſtants</hi> to ſtrengthen him in the <hi>buſtle</hi> of theſe <hi>conteſtations,</hi> and moſt ſure <hi>clues</hi> to lead him out of ſo difficult <hi>Maze<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> Nay! his undaunted reſolutions, like the <hi>Eagle,</hi> fear'd not to encounter the loud-<hi>tongu'd Thunder,</hi> and confron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that <hi>quarter</hi> of <hi>Heaven,</hi> where <hi>lightning</hi> and <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt</hi> moſt raged: witneſſe thoſe many ſpurns of <hi>Fortune</hi> he has received, and thoſe many <hi>ſhocks</hi> of <hi>envy</hi> he hath endured, and yet continues ſafe and whole. His <hi>wiſdome</hi> hath been ſo great that the ſubtill <hi>Serpent</hi> cannot out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrip,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:161821:9"/>and his <hi>innocence</hi> ſo ſpotleſſe, that the <hi>Doves</hi> is not more. In the generality of his <hi>actions</hi> he hath appeared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the ordinary <hi>levell</hi> of <hi>Princes,</hi> like a moſt noble <hi>ſcutcheon,</hi> upon which only the <hi>Almighty</hi> hath <hi>blazon'd</hi> all the <hi>bearings</hi> of <hi>vertue</hi> and <hi>honour.</hi> He hath manifeſted himſelf a Piece of that ſeaſon'd worth, that the <hi>pens</hi> of this <hi>Age</hi> cannot ſufficiently deſcribe, for if they ſhould attempt it, his <hi>vertues</hi> would <hi>preſſe</hi> in ſo thick together, that they'd <hi>choake</hi> the <hi>current</hi> of the ableſt <hi>fancy;</hi> being (indeed) not fit to be delivered with the ordinary liberty of <hi>ſpeech,</hi> but rather by the <hi>wel-ordered</hi> and <hi>majeſtick de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery</hi> of an <hi>Angell;</hi> But however,
<q>
                  <l>Illum aget pennâ metuente ſolvi</l>
                  <l>Fama ſuperſtes.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>In fine, no <hi>Prince</hi> ere ſhrin'd up ſo many <hi>vertues,</hi> or was more <hi>pious,</hi> or <hi>unfortunate,</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>—cui Pudor, &amp; Juſtitiae ſoror,</l>
                  <l>Incorrupta Fides; nuda<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Veritas,</l>
                  <l>Quando ullum invenient parem?</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Yet when he was removed from his <hi>Throne,</hi> they (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force) left him the greateſt <hi>dignity,</hi> for <hi>nobilitas ſola eſt at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> unica, virtus;</hi> and when he was diſpoſſeſt of <hi>three Kingdoms,</hi> yet ſtil he injoy'd a larger <hi>ſeignory,</hi> for <hi>virtus eſt optima poſſeſsio,</hi> but what would have been the iſſue of his <hi>impriſonment,</hi> Heavens <hi>all-diſcerning eye</hi> onely ſaw, <hi>Prona eſt Timori ſemper in pejus fides.</hi> In ſuch dubious caſes give us leave to fear the worſt. I believe they ſtrove to make him <hi>happy,</hi> but I as verily believe it muſt have been verified in the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> ſenſe, <hi>foelix ante obitum nemo.</hi> And <hi>Carisbrook-Caſtle</hi> I am as fully ſatisfied, was prepared with the ſame intention the <hi>murdering-Shirt</hi> was for <hi>Agamemnon;</hi> out of which it was impoſſible for
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:161821:10"/>him to ſcape. Ungratefull <hi>Ocean!</hi> who after this <hi>Suns</hi> long daies driving his troubleſome <hi>chariot,</hi> courting him into her boſome, to quench the <hi>thirſt</hi> of his <hi>Steeds,</hi> and to refreſh himſelf, turn'd to a <hi>bottomleſſe deep,</hi> and betray'd him into an <hi>inſatiable Gulph,</hi> where he (ô complementall <hi>treachery!</hi>) had been irrecoverably <hi>drown'd,</hi> but for thoſe loyall and unexpected hands, that are now <hi>boying</hi> him up again: And thanks be unto <hi>God</hi> for this timely <hi>appearing deliverance,</hi> and opening unto him a paſſage by ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected a <hi>dore.</hi> During this time of <hi>durance,</hi> what hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe was it for a <hi>King</hi> to own the <hi>latitude</hi> of <hi>three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms,</hi> who was thus confin'd to as <hi>few rooms;</hi> where he had little or no <hi>recreation,</hi> but what he receiv'd by that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flex of his many <hi>misfortunes,</hi> which by him were never <hi>merited,</hi> nor by us can be ſufficiently <hi>lamented.</hi> Here His <hi>patience</hi> indured the ſtricteſt <hi>touch,</hi> for the Miniſters of <hi>Sathan</hi> were ſet upon every ſide to <hi>buffet</hi> him; and his loweſt <hi>Vaſſals</hi> that ſought to undermine him, when they could not do it, raiſed themſelves high to <hi>cruſh</hi> him with their <hi>power.</hi> And now it was they acted all <hi>below-board,</hi> having their <hi>times</hi> and <hi>ſeaſons</hi> as <hi>darke,</hi> as the wiſhes of ſuch light haters could poſſibly <hi>lim</hi> out; ſhewing him leſſe <hi>mercy</hi> then his <hi>relation</hi> required, and more <hi>tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> then his <hi>faults</hi> could <hi>deſerve:</hi> which exceedingly ſtrengthned this ſuſpition that that <hi>Sword</hi> might ſecure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cut off, which ſo <hi>privately</hi> fetch'd its blow: the feare whereof to the ſouls of his loyall <hi>Subjects</hi> was really, <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinthio amarius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe, and many more his <hi>misfortunes</hi> were to be la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, becauſe they were his, and the rather beauſe (to the narroweſt obſerver) they ſeem'd ordain'd, to run pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel with his life; during which, like the noble <hi>Roman</hi> in his rolling <hi>Tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of <hi>nailes,</hi> which way ſoever he turns,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:161821:10"/>muſt needs feel ſomething that continually <hi>galls</hi> him: inſomuch, that many thought the beſt bleſſing they could deſire for him (<hi>death</hi> ſeeming to them his faithful <hi>friend</hi>) was to wiſh Heaven would ſend a <hi>writ</hi> of <hi>eaſe</hi> to his reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe <hi>labours,</hi> and ſo releaſe him from his growing <hi>ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows.</hi> 'Twas this very conſideration that purchaſed him ſome <hi>affections</hi> among thoſe narrow-<hi>ey'd</hi> attendants of his. <hi>Multis ille bonis flebilis occidit:</hi> and divers of their own party could not but look upon his <hi>afflictions</hi> with a pitiful diſlike: Nay! his bitter <hi>Enemies</hi> began to lament his <hi>diſtreſſed condition;</hi> his <hi>impriſonment</hi> alone, freeing him from the further ſtrokes of <hi>malice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what true <hi>Engliſh</hi> heart is it, that can hear the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars of his <hi>rough uſage</hi> and tranſcendent <hi>miſery,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out affording a noble <hi>compaſsion?</hi> really none; unleſſe ſuch as are hardned into a ſtif-neck'd <hi>inſenſibleneſſe.</hi> But I hope ſome gratefull <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> when he ſhall record the <hi>Annals</hi> of his <hi>misfortunes,</hi> will not let theſe paſſe, without being <hi>margin'd</hi> with a texted <hi>Ecce,</hi> the rather, becauſe it hath been the nature of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to behold <hi>diſtreſſes</hi> with a tender eye, and melting heart; conceiving it ever more noble to <hi>raiſe</hi> him up that is thrown <hi>downe;</hi> then to <hi>ſupport</hi> thoſe whom they have <hi>raiſed.</hi> For though <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune</hi> (that <hi>Tyrant</hi> to humane eſtate) hath exerciſed her rigorous power too much and long, yet now ſince ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to abate ſome of her <hi>cruelty,</hi> we may be invited (as by a good <hi>Omen</hi>) to aſſiſt his re-eſtabliſhment, her <hi>wheel</hi> is ever in a perpetuall <hi>motion,</hi> and 'tis probable <hi>His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty</hi> is now paſt the <hi>Nadir,</hi> and upon the <hi>aſcending ſide,</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>—quis neget arduis</l>
                  <l>Pronos relabi poſſe rivos</l>
                  <l>Montibus, &amp; Tiberim reverti.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:161821:11"/>
            <p> And now to behold happineſſe to approach when <hi>envy</hi> and <hi>malice</hi> had <hi>weaved</hi> ſuch ſtrong <hi>webs,</hi> that it lay not within the compaſſe of any <hi>Allye</hi> to break; to ſee delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance at hand when he was thrown beyond the hand of <hi>hope</hi> or <hi>help,</hi> no poſſibility ſhewing it ſelf to re-inſtate him into his <hi>paſt honours;</hi> is like a <hi>glory</hi> in the middle of an <hi>Eclipſe.</hi> But the paſſage through which <hi>Gods</hi> providence wanders, is alwaies <hi>miraculous:</hi> through how many ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall <hi>Meanders</hi> and unſeen waies, doth it begin to ſteale us: perhaps 'twill prove <hi>well</hi> for <hi>us,</hi> though 'twas <hi>bad</hi> for <hi>him,</hi> that he hath been thus long laid aſide; his <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues</hi> like a luſty <hi>painting</hi> never appeared <hi>faire</hi> and <hi>lively</hi> but at this <hi>remove.</hi> His abſence hath given our <hi>thoughts</hi> time to <hi>chew</hi> the <hi>cudd,</hi> through which reliſh we may ſtrengthen the opinion of his <hi>unvaluable worth;</hi> and in his worthy <hi>thoughts</hi> render our ſelves clea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>beast.</hi> And though his enemies <hi>malice</hi> hath <hi>ſhrub'd</hi> him into <hi>Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood,</hi> and great <hi>Oaks</hi> ſeldome grow to perfect <hi>Timber</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter once <hi>lopt;</hi> yet his humble <hi>patience</hi> will make him capable of <hi>ſpreading,</hi> ſpecially being beſet with ſo many interpoſing <hi>skreens</hi> which <hi>curb</hi> the imperious <hi>winds,</hi> and preſerve him from their <hi>blaſting</hi> power, and happily then ſhall we live under his protecting <hi>ſhelter.</hi> 'Tis true, the intermitting <hi>harſh noates</hi> of the Times has diſcompoſed many <hi>instruments:</hi> yet his diſpoſition continues ſet to his wonted ſweetneſſe, and like the <hi>Sun,</hi> is, <hi>Idem per diverſa.</hi> Nor need we doubt that the courſe of affaires can be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then happily ſteered, when we ſhall behold ſo able and honeſt a <hi>Pilot</hi> ſit at the <hi>ſterne</hi> again, whoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt skill, the croſſe <hi>tides</hi> (raiſed by theſe late <hi>ſtormes</hi>) hath juſtly commended.</p>
            <p>To Conclude, though the <hi>paſſages</hi> wherein we walke, ſeem (at preſent) <hi>obſcure,</hi> and <hi>uncertaine;</hi> yet doubtleſſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:161821:11"/>they'l aſſuredly lead our <hi>hopes</hi> to their expected end, what we cannot yet clearly <hi>ſee,</hi> we muſt ſtrive to <hi>ſcent</hi> out, and he that is content leiſurely to clime a <hi>hill,</hi> ſhal a great deale better his <hi>proſpect.</hi> If I may judge of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing <hi>day</hi> without <hi>erecting</hi> a <hi>figure,</hi> (and many times ſome generall <hi>judgments</hi> may be gathered from <hi>leſſer exactnes,</hi> as plain <hi>Country-men</hi> (though illiterate) can gueſſe at en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing weather by obſerving the <hi>colour</hi> of the <hi>Moone</hi>) I ſhould be very forward to aſſure this <hi>Nation</hi> of a cleare <hi>Horizon,</hi> wherein we ſhall reſtore <hi>Phoebus</hi> in his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>ſplendour,</hi> and our ſelves capable of receiving the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of his <hi>healing influence,</hi> which whilſt any fatall or envious <hi>interpoſition</hi> laſts, cannot deſcend upon us, nor our <hi>eyes</hi> be comforted with a <hi>beame</hi> naturally powerfull. But 'tis almoſt impoſſible (according to naturall cauſes) but that <hi>London</hi> (in the generality) muſt naturally affect <hi>Monarchy</hi> if <hi>Gemini</hi> be its <hi>Aſcendant,</hi> that affectionate <hi>conſtellation</hi> beholds <hi>Leo</hi> with a <hi>Sextile,</hi> which is counted the <hi>Regall Signe,</hi> and the <hi>Aſpect</hi> an <hi>aſpect</hi> of <hi>love</hi> and <hi>friendſhip:</hi> Nor wil this Kingdom (if under <hi>Aries</hi>) come behind, or ever indure any <hi>Government</hi> but what is <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchicall,</hi> for <hi>Aries</hi> is of the ſame <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>triplicity</hi> with <hi>Leo,</hi> and caſts to it a friendly <hi>Trine,</hi> (which is eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the moſt <hi>perfect</hi> and <hi>friendly Aſpect</hi>) nor can the <hi>Kingly Lion</hi> but cordially affect both thoſe <hi>ſignes,</hi> whom he ſo <hi>amicably</hi> beholds. So that notwithſtanding other <hi>malevolent Planets</hi> (either by unhappy <hi>poſition,</hi> or hatefull <hi>aſpect</hi>) have for ſome yeares impoyſon'd their <hi>nature;</hi> thruſting the <hi>Sun</hi> out of his <hi>exaltation,</hi> and converting the quality of <hi>Mercury</hi> to ill, by ſome <hi>malicious</hi> &amp; <hi>preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ray;</hi> yet ſurely ſuch will not alwaies prove <hi>ſtationary,</hi> but ſhortly remove: that the naturall force of theſe <hi>ſigns</hi> may ſhew their <hi>mutuall affection;</hi> And if either <hi>Kingdome</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:161821:12"/>or <hi>City</hi> will taſt the benefit of the <hi>Suns</hi> re-vivifying <hi>influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> now is the <hi>time</hi> to receive it; For in this years <hi>revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution</hi> the <hi>Kingly</hi> ſigne <hi>culminates,</hi> and <hi>Sun Almuten</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of poſited in <hi>Aries</hi> the <hi>Kingdomes</hi> ſigne and his owne <hi>exaltation,</hi> from whence he beholds <hi>Gemini</hi> with a loving <hi>Sextile,</hi> and (receives <hi>Mercury</hi>) Lord thereof into his <hi>exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation;</hi> whoſe <hi>power, poſition,</hi> and <hi>aſpect,</hi> (together with many agreeing <hi>Teſtimonies</hi> in that promiſing <hi>ſcheame</hi>) are all aſſurances of <hi>His Majeſties</hi> recruiting his <hi>honour,</hi> and ſtrong preſumptions of mutuall <hi>concord</hi> and <hi>agreement,</hi> between the <hi>King, Kingdome,</hi> and <hi>City.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That no more <hi>obſtacles</hi> then may run between us and our happineſſe, let us diſcover his <hi>ſafe</hi> and <hi>honourable</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment by our free and hearty <hi>invitations,</hi> leſt he be ſtollen again into a <hi>cloud;</hi> and this <hi>City</hi> ſuffer the <hi>ruine</hi> it is now ready to fall into: for by this and no other way can we recover our <hi>loſt renowne;</hi> which when we once a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain <hi>enjoy,</hi> let us learn to be ſo prudent as to <hi>preſerve</hi> it.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Nullum numen habes, ſi ſit prudentia.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
